const categories = [
  {
    "name": "Classical Literature",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "One of Walter Savage Landor's \"imaginary conversations\" portrays a discussion oflove between this man and Rhodope, his supposed lover. This native of Samos is giventhe power of speech by Isis in a fictional \"Romance\" named for him. Babrius renderedthis author's work into verse, and the scholar Phaedrus translated this writer intoLatin. In one of this writer's stories, one of the title figures spends the summer singingand in the winter is forced to beg the other for food. This author, probably born a (*)slave, also wrote a story in which the second title figure takes a nap midway through a race and ultimately loses. \"The Ant and the Grasshopper\" and \"The Tortoise and the Hare\" are by, for 10 points, what ancient Greek writer known for his fables?",
        "answer": "Aesop"
      },
      {
        "question": "Marilyn Hacker wrote a poem about how this author’s “guts clutched up like this.” This author wrote that “a human being without old age is not a possibility” in a poem translated under the title “The Beat Goes On.” In a poem by this author, the speaker says “it is as if my tongue has broken and immediately a subtle fire has run over my skin” while watching a man sitting opposite a woman and listening to her laughing. A. E. Housman wrote several adaptations of the so-called “midnight poem,” which was long attributed to this author. Commands like “take the bitter care from my mind” and “in all my battles fight as my comrade” end a poem by this author addressed to a “deathless” and “iridescent-throned” goddess. “Ode to Aphrodite” is one of the few substantially complete poems by, for 10 points, what ancient Greek poet who lived on the island of Lesbos?",
        "answer": "Sappho &lt;Other Literature&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Geography",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "Description acceptable. A paper by Urribarri, Rios, and Ferrer hoped that treatment with ammonia would allow this process to be used as a source of raw vegetable protein for the feeding of livestock. Pollution with poliaspartic acid and disruption of the hypolemnitic cone have been suggested as causes of this phenomenon, which may result in lower (*) oxygen levels that threaten the curbina fishery. Researchers at the University of Zulia blamed ships from Florida or Texas for starting this phenomenon by transporting an  ► invasive species of genus Lemna. For 10 points, what bloom of aquatic plants threatens the ecological health of a certain lake in western Venezuela?",
        "answer": "duckweed infestation of Lake Maracaibo (accept equivalents)"
      },
      {
        "question": "The \"Spreuer\" example of this feature in Switzerland contains Kaspar Meglinger's 17th-century paintings of the Danse Macabre. Examples of these features from Qing Dynasty China include the \"stepping toad\" and the \"eternal celebration.\" The longest feature of this type in the world, at Hartland in New Brunswick, was damaged by ice in the 1920s. The \"Burr (*) arch\" is a typical design for these structures, which exist at Kaufman's Distillery, White Rock Forge, and Landis Mill in Lancaster County, Pennsylvania. A 1992 novel by ► Robert James Waller centers on a photographer who is assigned to document these features in Madison County, Iowa. For 10 points, identify this kind of river crossing that is protected from rain and snow.",
        "answer": "covered bridges (prompt on \"bridges\")"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Physics",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "Diatomic boron anomalously lacks this property because the increased penetrationof s orbitals leads to s-p mixing. The Landau model explains this property in metals asLorentz interactions in a free electron gas. Molecules with this property form a singlepeak when shot through a Stern-Gerlach apparatus, because their net magneticmoment is zero. Graphite strongly possesses the (*) conventional form of this property,allowing it to be easily levitated. All noble gases have this property because their fully filled p orbitals can match together their opposing spins, cancelling them out. For 10 points, name this property of materials which induce a magnetic field opposite to an exterior magnetic field, in contrast to its para counterpart.",
        "answer": "diamagnetism [do not accept \"paramagnetism\"] "
      },
      {
        "question":"A bar being dragged down a metal rail by a constant external force may have an exponential decrease in its velocity because of this law. This equation explains how skin and proximity effects create eddies that heat up metals. A commutator and a rotating solenoid are used to generate power in a common application of this equation. This law gives the magnitude of the step-up or step-down in voltage from a (*) transformer. This law has a minus sign as a consequence of Lenz's law. It sets the electromotive force equal to the negative time derivative of the B flux through a current loop. For 10 points, name this equation giving the induced voltage from a change in magnetic field, the only one of Maxwell's equations named for an English scientist.",
        "answer": "Faraday's law of induction "
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "American History",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "One person at issue during this event was Charles Maultsby, who veered off-course and got lost. Atelegram whose first three words were \"YOUR ACTION DESPERATE\" was sent during this event byBertrand Russell. An operation misleadingly codenamed with the place name Anadyr preceded this event,which was chronicled in the memoir Thirteen (*) Days. The claim \"I am prepared to wait until Hell freezesover\" was made by UN Ambassador Adlai Stevenson during this event, which inspired the creation of a \"hotline\"between two world capitals. It was resolved when the Americans agreed to secretly remove its Jupiter weapons fromTurkey. For 10 points, name this tense period in 1962 which began when nuclear weapons were discovered in acountry ruled by Fidel Castro.",
        "answer": "Cuban Missile Crisis [prompt on October Crisis]"
      },
      {
        "question": "These people often earned funds for traveling through the credit-ticket system. The citizenship of a child of two members of this ethnicity was confirmed via the jus soli concept in an 1898 Supreme Court case. The Six Companies catered to people of this ethnicity, who were the subject of the Geary Act. These people were the target of the Rock Springs massacre and were initially attracted by (*) \"Gold Mountain\". People of this ethnicity benefited from the Magnuson Act of 1943 which largely repealed the 1875 Page Act. Large numbers of them worked on the Central Pacific Railroad. They were taxed by California's Anti-Coolie Act. For 10 points, name these people whose entry to the United States was restricted through a namesake \"Exclusion Act\".",
        "answer": "Chinese-Americans [or Chinese immigrants to the United States] "
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Biology",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "The first isolated aptamers were made of these molecules. These are the molecules that most frequently form stem loops or \"hairpins.\" Amounts of this molecule may be detected and quantified by a Northern blot. One type of this molecule has catalytic capabilities and forms the non-protein part of a snRNP  (\" snurp \") . Another type of this molecule is synthesized in the nucleolus and forms the non-protein part of (*)  ribosomes. This molecule carries amino acids to the ribosomes to make proteins. Introns are spliced out of these molecules, which contain uracil. For 10 points, name this class of nucleic acids, the \"messenger\" variety of which is transcribed from DNA.",
        "answer": "RNA  [or  ribonucleic acid s; accept more specific kinds of  RNA , like \" tRNA \", \" mRNA \", or \" rRNA \"; accept  ribozyme s; prompt on \"nucleic acids\"]"
      },
      {
        "question": " In prokaryotes, this process is down-regulated by the binding of GATC sequences to SeqA. During thisprocess, three molecules of PCNA act as a \"sliding clamp\" holding an enzyme to its substrate. Thisprocess starts at regions denoted \"ori,\" and is performed by an enzyme that yields the Klenow fragmentwhen cleaved. By growing E. coli in media with the 14 and 15 isotopes of nitrogen, the (*) Meselson-Stahlexperiment demonstrated that this process was semiconservative. In this process, which takes place during the Sphase of the cell cycle, the enzyme ligase I joins Okazaki fragments on the lagging strand, which diverges from theleading strand at this process's namesake fork. For 10 points, name this process of making two identical copies ofone DNA molecule. ",
        "answer": "DNA replication"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Computer Science",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "This entity is partitioned into blocks whose sizes are a power of 2 in the buddymethod. A unit that manages this entity is responsible for converting virtual addressesto physical addresses. This thing can be stored in a \"pool\" to avoid system calls. In somelanguages, this entity is \"marked\" as used or unused before it is subsequently\"sweeped.\" The \"dynamic\" type of this resource is often put on a (*) heap and can beallocated with the \"malloc\" function in C. To make contiguous pieces of this resource, one might run a \"defrag\" program. Garbage collection is an automatic process that frees up this resource, which can be \"leaked\" if it is never freed. For 10 points, name this resource whose \"random access\" type is a common form of information storage. ",
        "answer": "memory [accept virtual memory; accept random-access memory; do not accept or prompt on \"hard disk\"]",
      },
      {
        "question": "Maged (“MAG-ed”) Michael proposed a “hazard” version of these objects to overcome the shortcomings of shared lock-free objects. A smart version of this data type implements traits like “drop” and is useful for programing with concurrency. Lawson is credited with introducing this data type in the language PL/I (“P-L-one”). The calloc (“CAL-uck”) and malloc (“MAL-uck”) functions return a variable of this type. Deallocation can result in dangling examples of these variables, which can lead to a segmentation fault. Defining one of these variables in C can be done using an asterisk, which is also the symbol used when dereferencing a variable of this type. For 10 points, name these variables that specify a location in memory.",
        "answer": "pointers [accept hazard pointers or dangling pointers] &lt;Other Science (Computer Science)&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Auditory Fine Arts",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "One piece in this genre and number was played every year for Hitler's birthday by Wilhelm Furtwängler. In the last movement of that piece in this genre and number, the orchestra \"tries\" out the the themes of the previous three movements between cello-bass recitatives. That D-minor work in this genre and number is from 1824 and includes lyrics like \"Be (*)  embraced, you millions!\" and \"daughter from Elysium.\" Since composers like Bruckner and Mahler died after or around writing pieces in this genre and number, it is said to be \"cursed.\" For 10 points, a choral version of \"Ode to Joy\" ends Beethoven's piece of what genre and number?",
        "answer": "ninth symphonies  [accept obvious equivalents that include both the number  nine  and the genre symphony ; accept  curse of the ninth ; accept specific ninth symphonies like  Beethoven's ninth ] <J"
      },
      {
        "question": "A player of this instrument hypothesized that a \"third sound\" could be heard whentwo real tones sounded at the same time in an effect called a \"difference tone.\" JeffreyKalberg titled Chopin's Prelude No. 27 after a difficult sonata for this instrument andcontinuo whose larghetto affettuoso first movement is in 12/8 time. A set of pieces forthis instrument dedicated to \"all artists\" includes a piece in which it imitates the hornand flute; that piece is called \"The Hunt.\" Giuseppe (*) Tartini's \"Devil's Trill\" sonata is forthis instrument. Beethoven's Kreutzer Sonata is written for piano and this instrument. Demanding techniques like double-stops frequently appear in an Italian virtuoso's twenty-four caprices for this instrument. For 10 points, identify this primary instrument played by NiccolÃ² Paganini.",
        "answer": "violin"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "American Literature",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "A poem by this author calls a woman a \"thin brown mouse... living all alone/In this cold house\" and contrasts her with a woman who \"stayed home and scraped life with a fine tooth comb.\" This author of \"Sadie and Maud\" set a poem in a \"rented back room\" inhabited by two women \"who have lived their day\" and are \"Mostly Good\", for whom \"dinner is a casual affair\". In addition to \"The (*) Bean Eaters\", her works include a collection of poems about a girl growing up in Bronzeville called Annie Allen. Her most famous poem is about a group of pool players at \"The Golden Shovel\" who \"lurk late,\" \"strike straight,\" \"jazz June,\" and \"die soon\". For 10 points, name this first African-American Pulitzer Prize winner, the poet of \"We Real Cool.\"",
        "answer": " Gwendolyn Brooks [or Gwendolyn Elizabeth Brooks]"
      },
      {
        "question": "This sort of object provides the surname of an innkeeper who owns a mysterioussmoked-over oil painting and tells the protagonist that another character is outpeddling shrunken heads. In the first chapter of the novel in which he appears, thatprotagonist describes finding himself stopping before warehouses full of these objects.A character climbs into one of these objects with an idol named Yojo after falling (*) illwith a fever and later decorates it with carvings. A canoe-like object of this sort is reworked by a carpenter into a life-buoy. One of these objects made by Queequeg emerges from a whirlpool after the Pequod sinks. For 10 points, Moby Dick ends with Ishmael floating on what sort of object, usually used to store dead bodies?",
        "answer": "coffins [prompt on canoes, buoys, or sea chests]"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Religion",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "Soldiers adhering to this religion prayed to a goddess of light and the sun named Marici before battles.People float paper lanterns down a river at the culmination of a three-day summer festival in this religionfor honoring ancestors, called Obon. Atop Mount Hiei, many members of this religion's clergy trained forcombat. Two esoteric schools of this religion, introduced by Kukai and Saicho, were respectively known as(*) Shingon and Tendai. Practitioners of one form of this religion strive to attain an initial insight known as kensho,or satori, and practice the contemplation of statements and questions known as koans. For 10 points, name thisreligion which has blended heavily with Shinto in Japan, where the \"Zen\" type is particularly popular. ",
        "answer": " Buddhism [accept specific types, such as Zen Buddhism]"
      },
      {
        "question": "A classic manual on performing this action was written by Ibn al-Jazari. In South Asia, this action is uniquely performed with the pani patti method. Important scholars of this task had their writings distributed by disciples known as rawi. According to the hadith, people who are particularly adept at this task have the ability to intercede and bring up to 10 people to heaven. The addition of nunation increased the ease of performing this task properly. In order to perform this action correctly, adherents obey the rules of tajweed. An individual who can perform this action perfectly from memory is known as a hafiz. For 10 points, name this action performed by Sunnis during nightly Ramadan prayers, the reading of a holy text in Arabic.",
        "answer": "reciting the Quran [or reading the Quran; or qira’at; prompt on memorizing the Quran] &lt;Religion&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "World History",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "A few months after this conflict, two belligerents quarreled over the sinking of the Eilat. Gunnar Jarring's peace mission after this war partly failed due to the \"three no's\" of the Khartoum Resolution. After losing this war, a leader ceded power to his vice-president Zakaria Mohieddin, but popular support drew him back to office. UN Security Council Resolution 242 dealt with the territorial exchanges in this war, which began with an attack on 25 different (*) airfields after the Straits of Tiran were closed. In this conflict, the Sinai Peninsula and the Gaza Strip were seized from Gamal Abdel Nasser's Egypt. This war was fought six years prior to the Yom Kippur War. For 10 points, name this 1967 victory for Israel over its Arab enemies, concluded in less than a week.",
        "answer": "Six-Day War [or June War; or Third Arab-Israeli War; or 1967 Arab-Israeli War until mentioned] "
      },
      {
        "question": "A field marshal who ruled this country set up a system of local government called\"Basic Democracies\" and began a war with an infiltration operation codenamedGibraltar. This country later launched Operation Chengiz Khan to start a war ended bythe Simla Agreement. In 1953, rioters in this country called for the Ahmadiyyah sect tobe declared non-Muslim. In this country, a referendum about an Islamization programwas used to extend the term of (*) Zia al-Huq by five years. This nation launched the Kahuta Project to develop nuclear weapons under Zulfikar Ali, the father of a prime minister killed by a bomb in 2007. This country's \"Great Leader,\" Mohammed Ali Jinnah, was its first post-partition leader. For 10 points, name this country once led by Benazir Bhutto.",
        "answer": "Pakistan"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "British Literature",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": " An author who returned to this country, his ancestral homeland, in 1935 made his name with the novelWolf Solent. An author from this country wrote about people who \"though they sink through the sea theyshall rise again\" in a poem that describes a time when \"though lovers be lost love shall not\". A characterfrom this adopted home of John Cowper Powys (COO-per POW-iss) holds Edmund Mortimer captive andproposes lending his (*) magic to Hotspur's rebellion in Henry IV, Part 1. A poet from this country wrote \"Anddeath shall have no dominion\" and a poem that urges the addressee to \"Rage, rage against the dying of the light\".For 10 points, name this country, the birthplace of Owen Glendower and the author of \"Do not go gentle into thatgood night\", Dylan Thomas.",
        "answer": " Wales [or Cymru; prompt on Great Britain or the United Kingdom or the U.K.; do not accept or prompt on \"England\"]"
      },
      {
        "question": "This poet described floating in the ocean, seeing a butterfly overhead, andreminiscing about his dead wife in the poem \"Amphibian.\" The narrator of anotherpoem by this man claims \"man's reach should exceed his grasp, or what's a heavenfor?\" That narrator dreams of working on one of the \"four great walls in the NewJerusalem\" alongside Rafael and Leonardo while painting his wife Lucrezia. Otherartworks in this man's poetry include a bronze statue of (*) Neptune taming a seahorse cast by Claus of Innsbruck and placed near a painting of a woman who \"liked whate'er she looked on.\" The narrator of a dramatic monologue by this poet killed his wife because she had \"a heart too soon made glad.\" For 10 points, name this poet of \"Andrea del Sarto\" and \"My Last Duchess.\"",
        "answer": "Robert Browning"
      },
      {
        "question": "One of this author’s characters is called “astonishingly like Uncle Joe Stalin” in a book which says that this author’s magnum opus is “not good in spite of but especially because of its moral confusions.” Christopher Ricks wrote a book about this author’s “grand style.” A book-length “preface” to one of this author’s works was written by C. S. Lewis. A reader-response analysis of this author’s magnum opus has a title which plays on C. S. Lewis’s Surprised by Joy; that book by Stanley Fish is called Surprised by Sin. A William Empson book investigates whether this author succeeded in “justifying the ways of God to man.” For 10 points, name this author who William Blake claimed was “of the Devil’s party without knowing it” in reference to his Paradise Lost.",
        "answer": "John Milton &lt;British Literature&gt; Bonuses",
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Audiovisual Fine Arts",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "A character in this play describes hearing an oracle commanding him to \"Gore them like a bull!\" Inthis play, a morose nurse gives a speech about how babies must be taken care of because they cannotthink for themselves. A speech by this play's chorus begins \"Oh, the torment bred in the race.\" Two menspeak like Parnassians to gain access to the royal palace in this play, in which a woman dreams of a (*)snake that drinks milk from her breast, then bites her, drawing blood. This play opens with the disguisedprotagonist approaching his father's grave with Pylades and placing two locks of hair on it, after which he isrecognized by his sister Electra. For 10 points, name this play in which Orestes kills Aegisthus and Clytemnestra,the second in Aeschylus's Oresteia.",
        "answer": "The Libation Bearers [or Choephoroi]"
      },
      {
        "question": "An opera by this composer cast the castrato Giambattista as the knight Armando. In one of this composer’s operas, a scandalous ballet in the third act, meant to showcase its venue’s new gas lighting, starred Marie Taglioni as the Abbess Helena. This composer, whose final Italian-language opera was Il crociato in Egitto (“eel kroh-CHA-toh een ay-JEET-toh”), wrote an opera in which the explorer Vasco da Gama sings “O paradis” (“oh pah-rah-DEE”) on Selika’s island. An opera by this composer opens with a short prelude set to Martin Luther’s “Ein feste Burg” (“yne FESS-tuh BOORK”). The libretto for this composer’s opera L’étoile du nord (“lay-TWALL doo NOR”) was written by the inventor of the well-made play, Eugène Scribe (“oo-zhen screeb”). This composer wrote a “Ballet of the Nuns” as well as an opera in which Valentine and her lover Raoul, a member of the title religious group, are killed in the St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre. For 10 points, name this composer of grand operas such as Robert le Diable (“ro-BAIR luh dee-AH-bluh”) and Les Huguenots (“lay oog-NOH”).",
        "answer": "Giacomo Meyerbeer [or Jacob Liebmann Beer] &lt;Other Arts&gt;",
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Visual Fine Arts",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "Most of the poses in this painting are taken from Marcantonio Raimondi'sJudgement of Paris, although Raphael's The Miraculous Draught of Fishes may haveinspired the pose of the woman bending over in the background. The artist's brothersposed for the student wearing a tasseled hat in this painting. This painting was inspiredby the subject of Titian's Pastoral Concert. Victorine Meurent (meau-rahn) modeled for awoman in this painting who holds her right hand to her (*) chin. The unusual grouping ofcherries with figs in the basket in the foreground of this painting may be a parallel of the different states of clothing of the people in this work. For 10 points, name this scandalous 1862 Edouard Manet painting of an outdoor meal.",
        "answer": "The Luncheon on the Grass [or The Picnic or Dejeuner Sur L'Herbe or The Bath or Le Bain] "
      },
      {
        "question": " Joseph Koch decorated four rooms devoted to this author in the Villa Massimi. A character created bythis author bites his own fingers as he's embraced by some naked youth in a sculpture by Jean-BaptisteCarpeaux. He's not FranÃ§ois Villon, but this author provided the source material for a sculpture of anelderly former model who stares at the ground titled The Old Courtesan, and for the Atlas-like man in thesculpture (*) I Am Beautiful. A man bites the bow of a ship as this author, wearing a red hood, recoils in horror inan 1822 painting by Eugene Delacroix titled for his \"barque.\" In a sculpture inspired by this author, a man holds hishand to his chin in a thinking pose. For 10 points, name this author whose work inspired Rodin's The Gates of Hell.",
        "answer": " Dante Alighieri [or Durante degli Alighieri]"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "European Literature",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "In the months after the atomic bombing of Japan, this author created a darker version of one of his plays in collaboration with the actor Charles Laughton. In that play by this author, the title character’s daughter Virginia dies of dysentery (“DISS-en-TAIR-ee”) in a convent after being unable to find a husband. This author explained an acting technique that he called the gestus in his essay “A Short Organum for the Theater.” A play by this author ends with a copy of the Discorsi being smuggled out of Florence by Andrea Sarti. This dramatist popularized the “alienation effect,” exemplified by the stark scenery of a play in which Anna Fierling loses her children during the Thirty Years’ War. For 10 points, name this German author of Life of Galileo and Mother Courage and Her Children who was the main proponent of “epic theater.”",
        "answer": "Bertolt Brecht [or Eugen Berthold Friedrich Brecht] &lt;European Literature&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "This writer used the term “mattress-grave” for the bed that he was confined to for the last eight years of his life due to a mysterious paralytic illness. This author, who coined the word “Lisztomania,” wrote about a man “seized with a savage woe” who’d “rather look up at the mountain than down at the rocks below” in a poem that was set to music by Liszt. An otherwise minor play by this author is the source of the quote “Where they burn books, in the end they will also burn human beings.” This author described his journey from Paris to Hamburg in a long poem subtitled “A Winter’s Tale,” and also alluded to Shakespeare in the subtitle of a satire about an escaped dancing bear. In a short lyric poem, this author of Atta Troll described a golden-haired maiden on the Rhine who lures sailors to their deaths. For 10 points, name this German expatriate poet of “Die Lorelei” (“dee LOH-ruh-lie”).",
        "answer": "Heinrich Heine (“HY-nuh”) [or Christian Johann Heinrich Heine] &lt;European Literature&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Fine Arts Other",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "An artist created a series of ten square one-and-a-half meter canvases, including one titled for how this city “was all gold,” for a 1961 exhibition in this city titled Art and Contemplation. A modern art museum in this city is housed in the former home of the American heiress Peggy Guggenheim. James Whistler painted his Nocturne in Blue and Silver during an extremely productive period of time in this city following his lawsuit against John Ruskin, who himself wrote a three-volume study of this city’s architecture. The workshop of Giovanni Bellini was located in this city, which gives its name to a “school” of artists that includes Giorgione (“jor-JO-nay”) and Tintoretto. Before he moved to England, Canaletto produced a number of incredibly accurate large-scale vedute (“veh-DOO-tay”) of, for 10 points, the Piazza San Marco and the Grand Canal in what Italian city?",
        "answer": "Venice [or Venezia; accept Venice Was All Gold and The Stones of Venice] &lt;Painting&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "This musician’s group wrote a six-track album containing the songs “Calcutta Blues” and “Golden Horn,” inspired by a US State Department-funded tour through Eurasia. The reissue of one of this musician’s albums contains a rendition of “So This Is Love” as a bonus track; that album is titled [this musician] Digs Disney. This musician used a Joan Miró (“zhoo-AHN mee-ROH”) painting for the cover of an album whose title says it goes “further” than another of his albums. Another of this musician’s albums includes a piece whose beat structure alternates between 2 + 2 + 2 + 3 and 3 + 3 + 3 and whose title is inspired by Mozart. This collaborator of Paul Desmond had a penchant for unusual time signatures, as can be seen in “Unsquare Dance,” “Blue Rondo à la Turk,” and a song whose title references it being in 5/4. For 10 points, name this jazz pianist whose album Time Out contains “Take Five.”",
        "answer": "Dave Brubeck [or David Warren Brubeck] &lt;Other Arts&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Math",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "Yoshua Bengio (“YOSH-oo-ah BEN-jee-oh”) et al. argued that a prevalence of points with this property surrounded by high error plateaus present the main challenge to high-dimensional optimization, and these points are a specific case of points where functions can be reparameterized using Morse’s lemma. Deforming a contour integral toward one of these points is an approximation method called the method of steepest descent, which is alternately named for these points. The Hessian matrix has both positive and negative eigenvalues at these points that can be identified by the second derivative test. These points are critical points but not local extrema. For 10 points, name these points where a multivariable function curves up and down in different directions, named for resembling a piece of riding equipment.",
        "answer": "saddle points [accept minimax point; prompt on stationary points or (non-degenerate) critical points; do not accept or prompt on “minimum” or “maximum” or “extremum”] &lt;Other Science (Math)&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "One can construct a “resolution” of this object based on a given self-adjoint operator where this object is equal to an integral over the operator’s spectrum. The operation of this object and its conjugacy classes on irreducible representations are listed in the first column of a character table. A group’s component group is its quotient group over its connected subgroup that contains this object. Rngs (“rungs”) are named for the fact that they lack these things, making them the non-unital version of rings. An unknot is one of them under knot addition. A monoid is a semigroup that contains one of these elements. The composition of a function with its inverse yields this element. For 10 points, name this element that leaves other elements unchanged under the group operation, which is zero for addition.",
        "answer": "identity element [or identity function; accept multiplicative identity or additive identity] &lt;Other Science (Math)&gt;",
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "World Literature",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "The protagonist of a novel from this country invents a fake saint to support his bureaucracy, which synchronizes all the clocks in this country; that novel from this country is called The Time Regulation Institute. In another novel from this country, 500 cats are imported to kill rats in order to fight the bubonic plague. The narrator of that novel creates a siege weapon with a scholar to whom he bears a strong physical resemblance. The narrator of that novel from this country becomes the slave of a man known as Hoja. An author from this home country of Ahmet Hamdi Tanpınar created the poet Ka, who negotiates Blue’s release by ensuring that Kadife removes her headscarf during a production of The Spanish Tragedy. For 10 points, name this home country of the author of The White Castle and Snow, Orhan Pamuk.",
        "answer": "Turkey [or Republic of Turkey; or Türkiye Cumhuriyeti] &lt;World Literature&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "A woman kills a corrupt mayor near this geographical feature in a novel entitled God Dies by [this feature]. In a novel named for this feature, a nail polish bottle contains the red ink that Linnet Doyle’s husband Simon uses to fake an injury. An Anthony Sattin book named after this geographical feature is about how both Florence Nightingale and Gustave Flaubert (“flow-BAIR”) participated in the same trip along this river in 1849. Felicia Hemans’s (“HEM-inz’s”) poem “Casabianca” commemorates a battle that took place near this river. The protagonist of the novel Season of Migration to the North drowns in this river, though it is left ambiguous whether the narrator does so as well. An Agatha Christie novel is titled for a death on this river. The novels Palace Walk, Palace of Desire, and Sugar Street take place near this river. For 10 points, name this river, a city on which is the setting for Naguib Mahfouz’s Cairo Trilogy.",
        "answer": "Nile River &lt;Other Literature&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Mythology",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "In one story, the skin of one of these deities turns black after an encounter with a frenzied Shiva, who had just been shot by one of Kama’s magic arrows. A female one of these deities is honored along with her brother in the festival of Bhai-Dooj. That god, a daughter of the sun god Surya, is a twin of Yama. One of these deities was called to earth after the sixty thousand sons of Sagar were killed by the sage Kapila. After drowning the first seven of her children with Shantanu, that deity gave birth to a personification of Dyaus named Bhishma. One of these gods was held within the hair of Shiva after threatening to destroy the world and was created from the sweat of Vishnu’s feet. One of these gods is often depicted riding her mount Makara, who is half mammal and half fish. For 10 points, name these gods, who embody features like the Yamuna and the Ganges.",
        "answer": "river gods [or water gods; accept equivalents for “river” or “water”; prompt on Hindu gods] &lt;Mythology&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "In a Sioux myth, one of these objects is enchanted to appear overnight through the body of a young man who refused to sleep with an evil sorceress disguised as the man’s adopted sister. In the Welsh myth Math fab Mathonwy (“MOTH vob ma-THON-wee”), the hero Lleu (“th’LUH-ee”) turns into an eagle after his death and is found by his uncle overlooking a lake on one of these objects. It’s not an axe, but one of these objects was a symbol of Perun that represented the world in Slavic mythology. One of these objects in Hesse (“HESS-uh”) that was sacred to Thor was destroyed by St. Boniface in the 8th century. An oracle of Zeus at Dodona interpreted the rustling of the leaves of this kind of tree to divine the god’s will. A passage from Pliny (“PLIN-ee”) describes a Celtic ritual involving the removal of mistletoe from one of these trees. For 10 points, name this kind of deciduous tree whose acorns were consumed by Druids as a way of seeing the future.",
        "answer": "oak trees [accept Donar’s Oak or Thor’s Oak; prompt on trees] &lt;Mythology&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Philosophy",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "This book’s ideas provide the basis for a recent work of feminist philosophy by Charlotte Witt that argues in favor of “gender uniessentalism” (“yoo-nee-essentialism”). This work notes the superfluous nature of the phrase “footed two-footed animal” to argue that chains of “differentia” can be replaced by the last “differentia.” This work uses the example of a person with their eyes closed to illustrate the state of dunamis, or “potentiality,” which can transition to one of “actuality.” A thing’s “substance” is proposed to be “the primary cause of its being” in the final part of this work’s best-known section, Book Zeta. The name of this work, which opens with the phrase “All men by nature desire to know,” is often seen as an indication that its later compilers intended it to be read after its author’s works on natural science. For 10 points, name this work on “first philosophy” by Aristotle.",
        "answer": "Metaphysics [or Metaphysica] &lt;Philosophy&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "One book claims that humans use a form of “intuition” named for these entities to constitute “states of affairs” from “situations of affairs.” Heidegger’s Being and Time argues that these entities represent determinations regarding “beings unlike Dasein (“DAH-zyne”)” and contrasts them with “existentials.” Edmund Husserl distinguished between two types of these entities: ontological ones and ones “of meaning.” Preferring the term “predicaments” for these entities, Charles Sanders Peirce (“purse”) outlined three universal ones in a paper titled for a “New List” of them. Gilbert Ryle used an example of a visitor to Oxford viewing its buildings and asking “But where is the university?” to illustrate a type of “mistake” named for one of these entities. “Substance” and “quantity” are among a list of ten of, for 10 points, what entities proposed in a namesake work by Aristotle that attempts to inventory the structure of reality?",
        "answer": "categories [or category; accept categorical intuition, categories of meaning, ontological categories, kategoriai, category mistake, category error, “On a New List of Categories,” primary categories, and secondary categories] (The first clue refers to Husserl’s Logical Investigations.) &lt;Philosophy&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Classical History",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "The Treasure of Guarrazar contains 26 votive crowns and crosses offered to the Catholic Church by leaders of these people. These people’s namesake law code was promulgated by Chindasuinth and superseded the earlier Code of Leovigild. The last king of these people was killed by invading forces under Tariq ibn Zayid. The Kingdom of Asturias was founded by a leader of these people called Pelagius, who won the Battle of Covadonga. A king of these people allied with Flavius Aetius to win the Battle of the Catalaunian Plains, where he was killed. These people were pushed out of Gaul after their defeat at the Battle of Vouillé (“vwee-YAY”). These people sacked Rome in 410 under their leader Alaric. For 10 points, name these people who are contrasted with their eastern counterparts, the Ostrogoths.",
        "answer": "Visigoths [prompt on Goths] &lt;European History&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "A set of trade restrictions passed by this city was reinterpreted as a purely religious sanction in a 1972 book by British historian G. E. M. de Ste. Croix (“duh saint croy”), who also wrote a 1954 article about the “character” of this city based on a lecture about its “alleged unpopularity.” This city broke with precedent by establishing plantation-like, extraction-oriented colonies called cleruchies (“CLAIR-uh-keez”). The “fall” of this city’s empire titles the fourth volume of a history by Donald Kagan. This city’s citizens were credited with the line “The strong do what they can and the weak suffer what they must” in a fictionalized dialogue with the city of Melos. This city, whose trade was conducted by foreigners called metics, moved the treasury of the Delian League to this city in 454 BC. For 10 points, name this home city of Thucydides, which fought the Peloponnesian War with Sparta.",
        "answer": "Athens [or the Athenian Empire; accept The Character of the Athenian Empire; accept The Fall of the Athenian Empire] &lt;Ancient History&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Current Events",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "This leader required that nongovernmental organizations receiving 25,000 dollars or more in donations were required to label themselves as “foreign-funded.” This man rose to party leadership after protesting the unmarked burial of Pál Maléter (“pal mah-LAY-ter”) and three others in the Municipal Cemetery. Billboards reading “The people have decided. The country has to be protected” were erected after this leader approved a border wall against Serbia and Croatia. This leader made the creation of an “illiberal state” a founding principle of his Fidesz (“FEE-dess”) party. Shortly after the US Holocaust Museum denounced him for praising Miklós Horthy (“MEEK-lohsh HOR-tee”), his government printed propaganda posters depicting a grinning George Soros. For 10 points, name this authoritarian Prime Minister of Hungary.",
        "answer": "Viktor Orbán [or Viktor Mihály Orbán] &lt;Current Events&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "A legislator from this state, Ibraheem Samirah, was attacked as anti-Semitic for making a 2014 Facebook post saying that Ariel Sharon (“ah-ree-EL sha-ROHN”) “should burn a million times for every innocent soul” he killed. Another legislator from this state was called “Really, Really Boring” in a New York Times op-ed because of her emphasis on fixing Route 28. That state legislator was (*) Danica Roem, who became this state’s first transgender legislator in 2017. After the 2017 midterm elections, the Republicans retained control of this state’s legislature following a literal name-drawing from a bowl. In January 2019, this state’s governor was found to have taken a medical school yearbook picture with a man wearing blackface and another wearing KKK robes. For 10 points, name this state whose 2017 gubernatorial election was won by the embattled Democrat Ralph Northam.",
        "answer": "Virginia &lt;JH, Other&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Social Science",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "Gebser v. Lago Vista Independent School District established the criteria that in order to be held liable, school districts must have actual, not constructive, notice of this phenomenon and display “deliberate indifference” toward it. According to Barbara Gutek’s theory of this phenomenon, a form of “spillover” leads to the frequent experience of it by people in nontraditional roles. In Meritor Savings Bank v. Vinson, the Supreme Court adopted the category of “quid pro quo” as one form of this phenomenon, drawing on Catharine MacKinnon’s argument that it is an illegal form of discrimination. In deciding cases about this phenomenon, courts often try to determine whether it is sufficiently “severe or pervasive” to produce a “hostile environment” and employ the “reasonable woman standard.” For 10 points, name this two-word phrase that refers to bullying and coercion typically targeted towards women.",
        "answer": "sexual harassment [accept word forms and more specific forms, such as sexual harassment of students, sexual harassment of employees, etc.; prompt on harassment, sex discrimination, gender discrimination, or bullying until read] &lt;Social Science&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "Lennard Davis coined a portmanteau that pairs this concept with postmodernism to argue for a mode of thinking organized around “dependency and interdependence.” In Frontiers of Justice, Martha Nussbaum argues that John Rawls’s contractarianism is unable to fully account for this concept. A book by Rosemarie Garland-Thomson contrasts this concept with that of the “normate.” Advocates of “people-first language” argue that it works to prevent this concept from defining individuals. In the United States, the IDEA (“I-D-E-A”) requires people described by this term to be educated in the “least restrictive environment,” a practice also known as “mainstreaming.” A 1990 law requires employers to provide “reasonable accommodations” for Americans described by this term. For 10 points, name this term that refers to the restrictions experienced by people with conditions such as paraplegia and blindness.",
        "answer": "disability [or disabled; accept dismodernism and more specific answers that mention disability, such as mental or physical disability; prompt on descriptive terms such as impairment and handicapped, and specific examples such as blindness] &lt;Social Science&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Science Other",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "Two answers required. Though neither is related to pressure, these two quantities are measured in situ by CTD sondes (“sonds”), which can be paired with Niskin bottles to take samples. An abrupt increase in these two quantities in the Northern Atlantic is caused by the intrusion of MIW, which forms a distinct water mass below the common water. The meridional overturning circulation is primarily driven by gradients in these two quantities. Water in the Mediterranean Sea has high values of these quantities because of its low input and proximity to the Equator. These two quantities primarily determine the density of seawater, which is why Antarctic Bottom Water sinks. For 10 points, name the two driving forces behind the thermohaline circulation, which are often measured in degrees Celsius and parts per thousand.",
        "answer": "temperature AND salinity [accept thermohaline circulation until read; accept temperature AND conductivity in the first sentence; accept descriptions of “salinity” like salt level or salt concentration; prompt on just concentration for “salinity”] &lt;Other Science (Earth Science)&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "P Cygni (“SIG-nee”) profiles are spectroscopic features caused by this phenomenon. This phenomenon can be “driven” by photon absorption by particular spectral lines. It’s not an accretion disk, but a magnetic field forces this phenomenon to co-rotate with its source when it is within the Alfvén (“all-VANE”) radius. The “fast” form of this phenomenon forms from open regions of a magnetic field called coronal holes. This phenomenon causes mass loss in Wolf–Rayet stars. This phenomenon slows down abruptly at the termination shock, and it stops at the heliopause, where the interstellar medium begins. Comets’ ion tails always point away from a star due to this phenomenon. Charged particles in this substance interact with the Earth’s magnetosphere, producing auroras. For 10 points, name this stream of charged particles emitted from the outer regions of stars.",
        "answer": "stellar wind [or solar wind; prompt on interplanetary medium or IPM] &lt;Other Science (Astronomy)&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "Chemistry",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "Chemists who specialize in this substance use abbreviations for compounds like alite (“A-lite”) and belite (“B-lite”). An intermediate in the production of this substance called clinker is produced after calcination happens in a rotary kiln. Alkali-silicon reactions weaken this material by causing swelling, a problem termed this material’s “cancer.” Because this material gives off heat as it cures, it can be cooled with liquid nitrogen, or water can be pumped through it to avoid contraction-induced stress. Production of this substance accounts for around 5 percent of the world’s carbon dioxide emissions. This material includes a binder made from clay and limestone. This material’s low tensile strength is augmented by steel rebar in a common reinforced variety. For 10 points, name this material composed of an aggregate bound by cement used for large construction projects like bridges and dams.",
        "answer": "concrete [accept Portland cement until “alkali-silicon,” but prompt thereafter by asking “what material is the cement primarily used for?”] &lt;Other Science (Engineering)&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "Samples in this technique are commonly stored in “pucks,” which can be loaded using robots like ACTOR. Hauptman and Karle developed “direct methods” for this technique by solving the Sayre equation. The ARP/wARP suite in CCP4 is used for automated refinement in this technique. One value computed in this technique is also computed on a subset of the data to obtain its “free” form; that is the R-factor. In this technique, multiple isomorphous replacement or anomalous dispersion methods can help solve the phase problem. Incident radiation in this technique has a similar wavelength to atomic spacings, which allows the use of Bragg’s law. This technique was used to produce photo 51 by Rosalind Franklin, who determined the structure of DNA with it. For 10 points, name this technique that uses high-energy radiation to solve the structure of macromolecules.",
        "answer": "X-ray crystallography [or X-ray diffraction; or XRD; prompt on crystallography or diffraction] &lt;Chemistry&gt;"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "European History",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "This ruler was the last to employ architect Domenico da Cortona, who worked in the Loire valley to build the Chateau of Chambord to this ruler's specifications. This European ruler's navy besieged the city of Nice at the same time as the pasha Hayreddin Barbarossa. An anti-Catholic notice was covertly placed outside this man's bedchamber in the Affair of the Placards.This man met with an English monarch at a lavish meeting organized by Cardinal Wolsey, the Field of the Cloth of Gold. This man was captured at Pavia after his alliance with Suleiman the Magnificent brought the Ottoman Empire into western European politics. For 10 points, name this Valois king of France, a rival of Charles V of Spain who patronized Leonardo da Vinci.",
        "answer": "Francis I Valois [or Francois I; prompt on Francis]",
      },
      {
        "question": "On March 30, 1949, this country was rocked by nationwide protests against it joining NATO. This country was occupied by British forces during World War II after it was invaded in Operation Fork. The “Match of the Century” between Boris Spassky and Bobby Fischer was held in this country in 1972. This country submitted to the authority of a foreign king in the “Old Covenant” of 1262. In 1986, Mikhail Gorbachev and Ronald Reagan met at a summit in this country’s capital city that eventually resulted in the signing of the Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty. Disputes over fishing rights between this country and Britain led to the Cod Wars. This country’s parliament is the oldest in the world, meeting since 930, and is called the Althing. For 10 points, name this island nation whose capital is Reykjavík.",
        "answer": "Iceland [or Republic of Iceland; or Ísland] &lt;European History&gt; Bonuses"
      }
    ]
  },
  {
    "name": "History Other",
    "tossups": [
      {
        "question": "This industry was built up in the Balkans by Durad Crnojević (“tser-NOY-uh-vitch”), the Lord of Zeta. James IV gave Walter Chepman and Androw Myllar a monopoly of this industry in Scotland. In Paris, mistreated apprentices in this industry rebelled against their poor living conditions by killing their masters’ cats in the so-called “Great Cat Massacre.” A pioneer of this industry in Venice mass-produced objects called enchiridia (“en-kai-RID-ee-uh”). Benedict Anderson combined the name of this industry with “capitalism” in his book Imagined Communities. This industry was introduced to England by William Caxton. This industry’s “Revolution” started after a goldsmith from Mainz (“MINE-ts”) started using movable type. For 10 points, Johannes Gutenberg was a pioneer of what industry that mass-produces books?",
        "answer": "printing industry [or publishing industry; accept printing press capitalism; accept bookmaking industry until “books”] &lt;European History&gt;"
      },
      {
        "question": "The Glasgow (“GLAZZ-goh”) Gallery of Modern Art occupies a mansion formerly owned by William Cunningham, one of several merchant “lords” of this good based in 18th-century Glasgow. Thomas Willis claimed that no sellers of this good were infected during the Great Plague of London, during which this good was thought to prevent disease. This good was criticized in a (*) “counterblaste” by James I, which questioned why his countrymen would adopt the “barbarous and beastly manners of the wild, godless, and slavish Indians.” A mild and sweet strain of this crop was crossbred by the husband of Pocahontas, John Rolfe, who began the cultivation of this crop in the Jamestown colony. For 10 points, name this cash crop that was the major export of colonial Maryland and Virginia.",
        "answer": "tobacco [or Nicotiana tabacum; anti-prompt on particular products like cigarettes, cigars, snuff, etc.] &lt;AE, European History&gt;"
      }
    ]
  }
]

module.exports = { categories }